When the telegraph came along, it was clear that it was going to globalize the news industry. What would this lead to? Well, obviously, it would lead to world peace. The television, a medium that allowed us not just to hear but see, literally see, what was going on elsewhere in the world, what would this lead to? World peace. (Laughter) The telephone? You guessed it: world peace. Sorry for the spoiler alert, but no world peace. Not yet. Even the printing press, even the printing press was assumed to be a tool that was going to enforce Catholic intellectual hegemony across Europe. Instead, what we got was Martin Luther's 95 Theses, the Protestant Reformation, and, you know, the Thirty Years' War. All right, so what all of these predictions of world peace got right is that when a lot of new ideas suddenly come into circulation, it changes society. What they got exactly wrong was what happens next. The more ideas there are in circulation, the more ideas there are for any individual to disagree with. More media always means more arguing. That's what happens when the media's space expands. And yet, when we look back on the printing press in the early years, we like what happened. We are a pro-printing press society. So how do we square those two things, that it leads to more arguing, but we think it was good? And the answer, I think, can be found in things like this. This is the cover of "Philosophical Transactions," the first scientific journal ever published in English in the middle of the 1600s, and it was created by a group of people who had been calling themselves "The Invisible College," a group of natural philosophers who only later would call themselves scientists, and they wanted to improve the way natural philosophers argued with each other, and they needed to do two things for this. They needed openness. They needed to create a norm which said, when you do an experiment, you have to publish not just your claims, but how you did the experiment. If you don't tell us how you did it, we won't trust you. But the other thing they needed was speed. They had to quickly synchronize what other natural philosophers knew. Otherwise, you couldn't get the right kind of argument going. The printing press was clearly the right medium for this, but the book was the wrong tool. It was too slow. And so they invented the scientific journal as a way of synchronizing the argument across the community of natural scientists. The scientific revolution wasn't created by the printing press. It was created by scientists, but it couldn't have been created if they didn't have a printing press as a tool. So what about us? What about our generation, and our media revolution, the Internet? Well, predictions of world peace? Check. (Laughter) More arguing? Gold star on that one. (Laughter) (Laughter) I mean, YouTube is just a gold mine. (Laughter) Better arguing? That's the question. So I study social media, which means, to a first approximation, I watch people argue. And if I had to pick a group that I think is our Invisible College, is our generation's collection of people trying to take these tools and to press it into service, not for more arguments, but for better arguments, I'd pick the open-source programmers. Programming is a three-way relationship between a programmer, some source code, and the computer it's meant to run on, but computers are such famously inflexible interpreters of instructions that it's extraordinarily difficult to write out a set of instructions that the computer knows how to execute, and that's if one person is writing it. Once you get more than one person writing it, it's very easy for any two programmers to overwrite each other's work if they're working on the same file, or to send incompatible instructions that simply causes the computer to choke, and this problem grows larger the more programmers are involved. To a first approximation, the problem of managing a large software project is the problem of keeping this social chaos at bay. Now, for decades there has been a canonical solution to this problem, which is to use something called a "version control system," and a version control system does what is says on the tin. It provides a canonical copy of the software on a server somewhere. The only programmers who can change it are people who've specifically been given permission to access it, and they're only allowed to access the sub-section of it that they have permission to change. And when people draw diagrams of version control systems, the diagrams always look something like this. All right. They look like org charts. And you don't have to squint very hard to see the political ramifications of a system like this. This is feudalism: one owner, many workers. Now, that's fine for the commercial software industry. It really is Microsoft's Office. It's Adobe's Photoshop. The corporation owns the software. The programmers come and go. But there was one programmer who decided that this wasn't the way to work. This is Linus Torvalds. Torvalds is the most famous open-source programmer, created Linux, obviously, and Torvalds looked at the way the open-source movement had been dealing with this problem. Open-source software, the core promise of the open-source license, is that everybody should have access to all the source code all the time, but of course, this creates the very threat of chaos you have to forestall in order to get anything working. So most open-source projects just held their noses and adopted the feudal management systems. But Torvalds said, "No, I'm not going to do that." His point of view on this was very clear. When you adopt a tool, you also adopt the management philosophy embedded in that tool, and he wasn't going to adopt anything that didn't work the way the Linux community worked. And to give you a sense of how enormous a decision like this was, this is a map of the internal dependencies within Linux, within the Linux operating system, which sub-parts of the program rely on which other sub-parts to get going. This is a tremendously complicated process. This is a tremendously complicated program, and yet, for years, Torvalds ran this not with automated tools but out of his email box. People would literally mail him changes that they'd agreed on, and he would merge them by hand. And then, 15 years after looking at Linux and figuring out how the community worked, he said, "I think I know how to write a version control system for free people." And he called it "Git." Git is distributed version control. It has two big differences with traditional version control systems. The first is that it lives up to the philosophical promise of open-source. Everybody who works on a project has access to all of the source code all of the time. And when people draw diagrams of Git workflow, they use drawings that look like this. And you don't have to understand what the circles and boxes and arrows mean to see that this is a far more complicated way of working than is supported by ordinary version control systems. But this is also the thing that brings the chaos back, and this is Git's second big innovation. This is a screenshot from GitHub, the premier Git hosting service, and every time a programmer uses Git to make any important change at all, creating a new file, modifying an existing one, merging two files, Git creates this kind of signature. This long string of numbers and letters here is a unique identifier tied to every single change, but without any central coordination. Every Git system generates this number the same way, which means this is a signature tied directly and unforgeably to a particular change. This has the following effect: A programmer in Edinburgh and a programmer in Entebbe can both get the same -- a copy of the same piece of software. Each of them can make changes and they can merge them after the fact even if they didn't know of each other's existence beforehand. This is cooperation without coordination. This is the big change. Now, I tell you all of this not to convince you that it's great that open-source programmers now have a tool that supports their philosophical way of working, although I think that is great. I tell you all of this because of what I think it means for the way communities come together. Once Git allowed for cooperation without coordination, you start to see communities form that are enormously large and complex. This is a graph of the Ruby community. It's an open-source programming language, and all of the interconnections between the people -- this is now not a software graph, but a people graph, all of the interconnections among the people working on that project — and this doesn't look like an org chart. This looks like a dis-org chart, and yet, out of this community, but using these tools, they can now create something together. So there are two good reasons to think that this kind of technique can be applied to democracies in general and in particular to the law. When you make the claim, in fact, that something on the Internet is going to be good for democracy, you often get this reaction. (Music) (Laughter) Which is, are you talking about the thing with the singing cats? Like, is that the thing you think is going to be good for society? To which I have to say, here's the thing with the singing cats. That always happens. And I don't just mean that always happens with the Internet, I mean that always happens with media, full stop. It did not take long after the rise of the commercial printing press before someone figured out that erotic novels were a good idea. (Laughter) You don't have to have an economic incentive to sell books very long before someone says, "Hey, you know what I bet people would pay for?" (Laughter) It took people another 150 years to even think of the scientific journal, right? So -- (Laughter) (Applause) So the harnessing by the Invisible College of the printing press to create the scientific journal was phenomenally important, but it didn't happen big, and it didn't happen quick, and it didn't happen fast, so if you're going to look for where the change is happening, you have to look on the margins. So, the law is also dependency-related. This is a graph of the U.S. Tax Code, and the dependencies of one law on other laws for the overall effect. So there's that as a site for source code management. But there's also the fact that law is another place where there are many opinions in circulation, but they need to be resolved to one canonical copy, and when you go onto GitHub, and you look around, there are millions and millions of projects, almost all of which are source code, but if you look around the edges, you can see people experimenting with the political ramifications of a system like that. Someone put up all the Wikileaked cables from the State Department, along with software used to interpret them, including my favorite use ever of the Cablegate cables, which is a tool for detecting naturally occurring haiku in State Department prose. (Laughter) Right. (Laughter) The New York Senate has put up something called Open Legislation, also hosting it on GitHub, again for all of the reasons of updating and fluidity. You can go and pick your Senator and then you can see a list of bills they have sponsored. Someone going by Divegeek has put up the Utah code, the laws of the state of Utah, and they've put it up there not just to distribute the code, but with the very interesting possibility that this could be used to further the development of legislation. Somebody put up a tool during the copyright debate last year in the Senate, saying, "It's strange that Hollywood has more access to Canadian legislators than Canadian citizens do. Why don't we use GitHub to show them what a citizen-developed bill might look like?" And it includes this very evocative screenshot. This is a called a "diff," this thing on the right here. This shows you, for text that many people are editing, when a change was made, who made it, and what the change is. The stuff in red is the stuff that got deleted. The stuff in green is the stuff that got added. Programmers take this capability for granted. No democracy anywhere in the world offers this feature to its citizens for either legislation or for budgets, even though those are the things done with our consent and with our money. Now, I would love to tell you that the fact that the open-source programmers have worked out a collaborative method that is large scale, distributed, cheap, and in sync with the ideals of democracy, I would love to tell you that because those tools are in place, the innovation is inevitable. But it's not. Part of the problem, of course, is just a lack of information. Somebody put a question up on Quora saying, "Why is it that lawmakers don't use distributed version control?" This, graphically, was the answer. (Laughter) (Laughter) (Applause) And that is indeed part of the problem, but only part. The bigger problem, of course, is power. The people experimenting with participation don't have legislative power, and the people who have legislative power are not experimenting with participation. They are experimenting with openness. There's no democracy worth the name that doesn't have a transparency move, but transparency is openness in only one direction, and being given a dashboard without a steering wheel has never been the core promise a democracy makes to its citizens. So consider this. The thing that got Martha Payne's opinions out into the public was a piece of technology, but the thing that kept them there was political will. It was the expectation of the citizens that she would not be censored. That's now the state we're in with these collaboration tools. We have them. We've seen them. They work. Can we use them? Can we apply the techniques that worked here to this? T.S. Eliot once said, "One of the most momentous things that can happen to a culture is that they acquire a new form of prose." I think that's wrong, but -- (Laughter) I think it's right for argumentation. Right? A momentous thing that can happen to a culture is they can acquire a new style of arguing: trial by jury, voting, peer review, now this. Right? A new form of arguing has been invented in our lifetimes, in the last decade, in fact. It's large, it's distributed, it's low-cost, and it's compatible with the ideals of democracy. The question for us now is, are we going to let the programmers keep it to themselves? Or are we going to try and take it and press it into service for society at large? Thank you for listening. (Applause) (Applause) Thank you. Thank you. (Applause)
Cuando surgió el telégrafo estaba claro que iba a globalizar el mundo de las noticias. Y esto, ¿a qué llevaría? Bueno, obviamente, llevaría a la paz mundial. La televisión, un medio que nos permitió no sólo oír sino ver, literalmente ver, qué estaba ocurriendo en otras partes del mundo, ¿eso a qué conllevaría? A la paz mundial. (Risas) ¿El teléfono? Adivinaron: a la paz mundial. Siento decirlo, pero no trajo la paz mundial. Todavía no. Incluso la imprenta, incluso la imprenta se suponía que era una herramienta que impondría la hegemonía intelectual católica en toda Europa. En cambio, trajo "Las 95 tesis" de Martín Lutero, la Reforma Protestante y, ya saben, la Guerra de los Treinta Años. De acuerdo, pero en lo que todas estas predicciones de paz acertaron es que cuando, de repente, empiezan a circular muchas ideas nuevas, eso cambia la sociedad. Se equivocaron en lo que ocurriría después. Cuanto más ideas hay en circulación, hay más ideas con las que no estar de acuerdo a nivel individual. Más medios siempre significa más discusiones. Eso es lo que ocurre cuando se expande el espacio de medios. Sin embargo, si nos retrotraemos a la imprenta en los primeros años, nos gusta lo que pasó. Somos una sociedad proimprenta. Entonces, ¿cómo conciliar esas dos cosas? nos lleva a discusiones, pero ¿nos parece algo bueno? Creo que la respuesta está en este tipo de cosas. Esta es la portada de "Philosophical Transactions", la primera revista científica publicada en inglés a mediados del siglo XVII, creada por un grupo de personas que se autodenominaba "El Colegio Invisible", un grupo de filósofos de la naturaleza que sólo más tarde se autodenominarían científicos, que querían mejorar la forma en que los filósofos naturales discutían y para eso tenían que hacer dos cosas. Necesitaban apertura. Tenían que crear una norma que dijera, cuando uno hace un experimento tiene que publicar no sólo sus afirmaciones, sino cómo hizo uno el experimento. Si no nos dices cómo lo hiciste, no te creeremos. Lo otro que necesitaban era velocidad. Tenían que sincronizar rápidamente con lo que sabían otros filósofos naturales. De otro modo, no se podrían mantener las discusiones apropiadas. Claramente, la imprenta era el medio correcto para esto, pero el libro era la herramienta incorrecta. Era demasiado lento. Fue así que inventaron la revista científica como una forma de sincronizar la discusión en la comunidad de científicos naturales. La revolución científica no fue producto de la imprenta. Fue producto de los científicos pero no se habría creado de no haber contado con la herramienta de la imprenta. Y, ¿qué hay de nosotros, de nuestra generación y de nuestra revolución mediática, Internet? Bueno, ¿predicciones de paz? Verifiquen. (Risas) ¿Más discusión? Premio de oro para esa. (Risas) Digo, YouTube es una mina de oro. (Risas) ¿Mejor discusión? Esa es la cuestión. Por eso estudio medios sociales, es decir, en una primera aproximación, veo a la gente discutir. Y si tuviera que elegir un grupo que creo es nuestro Colegio Invisible, es el grupo humano de nuestra generación que trata de tomar estas herramientas y plasmarlas en servicio no en busca de más, sino de mejores discusiones, me quedaría con los programadores de código abierto. La programación es una relación tripartita entre un programador, algo de código y la computadora que lo ejecuta; pero las computadoras son célebres por interpretar instrucciones de forma inflexible. Es extremadamente difícil escribir un conjunto de instrucciones que la computadora sepa ejecutar y eso si interviene una sola persona. En cuanto pones a más de una persona a programar, es muy fácil que cualquiera sobrescriba el trabajo del otro si trabajan en el mismo archivo, o que envíen instrucciones incompatibles que simplemente provoquen un colapso y este problema se acrecienta conforme intervienen más programadores. En una primera aproximación, el problema de gestionar un gran proyecto de software consiste en mantener bajo control este caos social. Ahora, durante décadas ha existido una solución canónica a este problema, que implica usar algo llamado "sistema de control de versiones". Y un sistema de control de versiones hace justamente eso. Proporciona una copia canónica del software de un servidor de algún lado. Los únicos programadores que pueden modificarlo son aquellos con permisos específicos para acceder al mismo, y sólo pueden acceder a la subsección de código sobre la que tienen permisos de edición. Y al graficar diagramas de sistemas de control de versiones, los diagramas siempre tienen un aspecto como éste. Correcto. Parecen organigramas. Y no hay que esforzarse mucho para ver las ramificaciones políticas de un sistema como este. Es feudalismo: un propietario, muchos obreros. Está bien para la industria del software comercial. Es el Office de Microsoft. Es el Photoshop de Adobe. La empresa es propietaria del software. Los programadores van y vienen. Pero hubo un programador que decidió que esta no era forma de trabajar. Se trata de Linus Torvalds. Torvalds es el programador de código abierto más famoso; creó Linux, obviamente, y observó la manera en la que el movimiento de código abierto había abordado el problema. El software de código abierto, la promesa central de la licencia de código abierto, es que todos deberían tener acceso al código fuente todo el tiempo, pero claro, esto crea la amenaza del caos que hay que evitar para conseguir que algo funcione. La mayoría de los proyectos de código abierto asomaron la nariz y adoptaron el sistema de gestión feudal. Pero Torvalds dijo: "No, no lo haré". Su punto de vista sobre este tema fue muy claro. Cuando uno adopta una herramienta, también adopta la filosofía de gestión que conlleva esa herramienta y él no adoptaría algo que no funcionara a la manera de la comunidad de Linux. Y para darles una idea de lo enorme que era una decisión así, este es el mapa de las dependencias internas de Linux dentro del sistema operativo Linux, qué subpartes del programa dependen de otras subpartes para funcionar. Es un proceso sumamente complicado. Es un programa sumamente complicado y sin embargo, durante años, Torvalds lo dirigió no con herramientas automatizadas, sino desde su correo. Las personas literalmente le enviaban los cambios que habían acordado, y él los combinaba a mano. Y luego, 15 años después, al mirar Linux y analizar el trabajo de la comunidad dijo: "Creo que sé cómo escribir un sistema de control de versiones para personas libres". Y lo llamó "Git". Git es un control de versiones distribuido. Tiene dos grandes diferencias con los sistemas tradicionales de control de versiones. La primera es que hace honor a la promesa filosófica del código abierto. Todo el que trabaja en un proyecto tiene acceso a todo el código fuente, todo el tiempo. Y al graficar el flujo de trabajo de Git se usan gráficos que tienen este aspecto. Y no hay que entender el significado de los círculos, las cajas y las flechas para ver que ésta es una forma mucho más complicada de trabajar que la provista por los sistemas comunes de control de versiones. Pero esto es también lo que trae nuevamente el caos, y esta es la segunda gran innovación de Git. Esta es una captura de pantalla de GitHub, el principal servicio de alojamiento de Git, y cada vez que un programador usa Git para hacer cualquier tipo de cambio, para crear un nuevo archivo o modificar uno existente, para combinar dos archivos, Git crea esta firma. Esta larga cadena de números y letras de aquí es un identificador único asociado a cada cambio, pero sin una coordinación central. Cada sistema Git genera este número de la misma manera, lo que significa que es una firma infalsificable asociada directamente a un cambio particular. Esto tiene el siguiente efecto: un programador en Edimburgo y uno en Entebbe pueden ambos tomar una copia del mismo software. Cada uno puede hacer cambios y combinarlos después de eso, incluso desconociendo de antemano la existencia el uno del otro. Esto es cooperación sin coordinación. Este es el gran cambio. Pero no les cuento todo esto para convencerlos de que es genial que los programadores de código abierto tengan una herramienta que respalde su filosofía de trabajo, aunque creo que es genial. Les cuento todo esto por lo que creo que significa en materia de unión de comunidades. En cuanto Git permitió la cooperación sin coordinación, se empezaron a ver formas comunitarias enormemente grandes y complejas. Este es un gráfico de la comunidad de Ruby. Es un lenguaje de programación de código abierto y todas las conexiones interpersonales —este ya no es un gráfico del software, sino de personas— todas las interconexiones entre personas que trabajan en ese proyecto... no parece un organigrama. Parece un "desorganigrama" y no obstante en esta comunidad, usando estas herramientas, ahora pueden crear algo juntos. Hay dos grandes razones para pensar que este tipo de técnica puede aplicarse a las democracias en general y en particular a la ley. De hecho, si uno afirma que algo de Internet será bueno para la democracia, a menudo obtiene esta reacción. (Música) (Risas) ¿Estás hablando del video de los gatos que cantan? ¿Eso es lo que crees que será bueno para la sociedad? A lo que respondo que el quid de los gatos que cantan es que siempre ocurre. Y no sólo quiero decir que ocurre con Internet, me refiero a que siempre ocurre con los medios, punto. No pasó mucho tiempo luego del auge de la imprenta comercial hasta que alguien se dio cuenta de que las novelas eróticas eran una buena idea. (Risas) No hizo falta un incentivo económico para vender libros; mucho antes alguien dijo: "¿Sabes lo que apuesto? que la gente comprará". (Risas) Hicieron falta otros 150 años para que la gente pensara en la revista científica, ¿sí? (Risas) (Aplausos) El aprovechamiento que el Colegio Invisible hizo de la imprenta para crear la revista científica fue extraordinariamente importante, pero no ocurrió a lo grande, tampoco ocurrió en forma rápida. Para ver desde dónde viene el cambio hay que mirar en los márgenes. La ley también tiene una relación de dependencia. Este es un gráfico del Código Fiscal de EE.UU., y la dependencia de una ley de otras leyes para el efecto conjunto. Allí está como sitio para la gestión de código fuente. Pero también está el hecho de que la ley es otro lugar donde circulan muchas opiniones, pero tienen que resolverse en una copia canónica. Y si vamos a GitHub y miramos los alrededores hay millones y millones de proyectos, casi todos de código fuente, pero si miramos en los bordes, se puede ver a la gente que experimenta con las ramificaciones políticas de un sistema como ese. Alguien puso todos los cables filtrados del Departamento de Estado, junto con el software usado para interpretarlos; eso incluye mi uso favorito de las filtraciones: una herramienta para detectar haikus naturales en la prosa del Departamento de Estado. (Risas) Correcto. (Risas) El Senado de Nueva York puso algo llamado Open Legislation, también alojado en GitHub, nuevamente, debido a razones de actualización y fluidez. Se puede ir, seleccionar un senador y luego ver los proyectos de ley que patrocinó. Alguien con seudónimo Divegeek subió el código de Utah, las leyes del estado de Utah, y lo subieron allí no sólo para distribuir el código, sino con la posibilidad muy interesante de que esto pueda usarse para favorecer el desarrollo de la legislación. Alguien subió una herramienta durante el debate de derechos de autor el año pasado en el Senado, que decía: "Es extraño que Hollywood tenga más acceso a los legisladores canadienses que los ciudadanos canadienses. ¿Por qué no usar GitHub para mostrarles cómo sería un proyecto de ley ciudadano?" Esta es una captura de pantalla muy evocadora. Esto se llama "diff", esto de la derecha. Muestra, en un texto editado por muchas personas, cuándo se hizo un cambio, quién lo hizo y cuál es el cambio. Lo que está en rojo es lo que se borró. Lo que está en verde es lo que se añadió. Los programadores dan esto por sentado. Ninguna democracia del mundo ofrece esta posibilidad a sus ciudadanos para la legislación o para los presupuestos, a pesar de ser cosas hechas con nuestro consentimiento y nuestro dinero. Me encantaría decirles que el hecho de que los programadores de código abierto hayan elaborado un método colaborativo a gran escala, distribuido, económico, en sintonía con los ideales democráticos, me encantaría decirles que dado que existen esas herramientas, la innovación es inevitable. Pero no lo es. Parte del problema, por supuesto, es sólo falta de información. Alguien publicó una pregunta en Quora: "¿Por qué los legisladores no usan control de versiones distribuido?" Esta es la respuesta gráfica. (Risas) (Risas) (Aplausos) De hecho, eso es parte del problema, pero sólo parte. El problema más grande, claro, es el poder. Las personas que experimentan la participación no tienen poder legislativo, y las personas que tienen poder legislativo no experimentan la participación. Están experimentando la apertura. No hay democracia que se precie que no tenga una medida de transparencia, pero la transparencia es la apertura en una sola dirección, y otorgar un tablero sin volante nunca ha sido una promesa troncal de una democracia a sus ciudadanos. Piénsenlo. Lo que llevó las opiniones de Martha Payne al público fue una pieza de tecnología, pero lo que las mantenía era la voluntad política. Fue la expectativa de los ciudadanos de que ella no fuera censurada. Ese es el estado actual de estas herramientas colaborativas. Las tenemos. Las hemos visto. Funcionan. ¿Podemos usarlas? ¿Podemos aplicar las técnicas que funcionaron aquí, allí? T.S. Eliot dijo una vez: "Una de las cosas más trascendentales que le puede ocurrir a una cultura es adquirir una nueva forma de prosa". Creo que eso está mal, pero... (Risas) Creo que está bien para discutir. ¿Cierto? Algo trascendental que puede ocurrirle a una cultura es adquirir un nuevo estilo de discusión: juicio por jurado, voto, revisión por pares, ahora esto. ¿Bien? En nuestra vida, se ha inventado una nueva forma de discusión; en la última década, de hecho. Es en grande, distribuida, económica y compatible con los ideales democráticos. La pregunta ahora es, ¿dejaremos que los programadores se la guarden para sí mismos? ¿O trataremos de tomarla para ponerla al servicio de la sociedad en general? Gracias por escuchar. (Aplausos) (Aplausos) Gracias. Gracias. (Aplausos)